of your future money podcast. The show really will go in depth in some of the big topics
happening in the crypto community. And today, I'm very excited to be joined by my good friend,
Pascal Gucci, the CEO of Ledger, to really talk about the latest trends that we are seeing in the
field of hardware wallets on self custody and the broader industry as a whole. Pascal, great to
have you with us on the show. Great to be here with you. Thank you for having me. You know, fun
fact about Pascal, I think many people know you as a chairman and CEO of Ledger. But interesting
fact about you, by the way, first, I know you're a back country skier. And second is you have a
restaurant in Paris. And another from the fact, I learned recently that you were until recently
one of the, you know, few French entrepreneurs with two billion dollar companies under your belt,
you know, that's a pretty big mix of achievements in a short time. Thank you. Actually, I think I
was the only one to have two. And then we are, I think we're two now. And I'm sad. And I'm happy
and sad at the same time. And I said to lose the title, what I think is my title. But I'm happy
because the second guy is actually my friend, Nicola, who I used to be with is at Creo, one of
the founders at Creo, was his new startup now and made it a billion dollar company. So I'm very
happy that he joined the club of like two timers, two timers unicorn. We are reading hearts.
You know, the first time may be luck, but the second time that's where there's talent skill or
craziness time will tell, I guess. Do it once you look it, do it twice, you're good. We'll see.
Look, we still have to do a lot of things with later. So this is not over yet.
Let's go. What's your restaurant in Paris? It was in the Marie, I think you told me, right?
Yeah. Well, so I did that. So the restaurant is actually tied to crypto because I started my
crypto company, Kaiko, you know, it's a data company back in 2014, almost would be on as running the
company. But in 2014, there was not much to do in crypto. Like, I'm not a coder, you see, so I
couldn't call it. So what was I going to do? So I decided there was a friend of mine that we're
going to do our restaurants. Like we talked about that for ages with my friends, but we decided to
do it. And so I could do it because I didn't have so much to do in crypto. And so I built the
restaurant in in Paris. And so and the restaurant is still going and it's going there. I'm still
there, right? Oh, yeah. So the restaurant has been going for, I don't know, eight years now,
because we didn't start it right away in 2014. It was more 15. And I think we opened in 16 or
something like that. It's been going on for a long time. It's a good success. Like, you know,
it's very nice. And it's been the home of like many crypto parties. Well, what's it called? Here,
we're going free plugging of the restaurant on the future of money. Yeah. ISTR. So Americans,
we'll call it like ISTR maybe something like that is it means oysters in Brittany.
Here we go. I love it. Well, Pascal, let's talk about I know we can talk about food all day,
but let's jump into crypto and a lot of topics I want to discuss with you today. But first of
all, before we start, can you give a bit of update about about yourself about your background and
then give us the the what is ledger? And then I separate I want to talk about stacks and some
of the new developments, but we'd be good to give the audience a bit of background on yourself,
especially for those who have the who are hearing you for the first time.
Yeah, I mean, you know, I'm French. I was born in Paris, born and raised in Paris. And I sort of
stumbled upon the internet in 2000. This is where and when I started my career. And then, you know,
it felt like at the time sort of building the internet, especially with online advertising that
was sort of my specialty, sitting, you know, banners, clicks and online advertising, basically,
you know, marketing and direct marketing. And I've done that for until 2013, between 2004 and
2008, I was at Yahoo, which was very lucky because at the time Yahoo was really the internet. And
so I could learn sort of everything at Yahoo. And then I took that knowledge through a small
company at the time called Creteo. And I have the three founders to change the business model,
pivot to an advertising business model. And we sort of invented the personalized retargeting,
you know, those annoying ads that follow you all around the web with the products that you might
like, you know, that's I claim that's our invention. And we certainly build like a category leader
in that space, you know, we went from Paris to having a team everywhere in the world. We had
at the time of the IPO is the only French company actually that IPO in the past 20 years at the
NASDAQ for between two and three billion dollars at the time. So it was a big deal. The company was
making billions in revenue at a few thousand employees, etc. Everywhere in the world, you know,
from Japan all the way to the United States and every country, you know, in between. So it was a
fantastic experience. And then from there, then I was, you know, sort of so searching and trying
to figure out what to do next. And I stumble, stumble upon Bitcoin in 2014. I met with once
SSRS, who is the super famous Bitcoiner and the guy who did Zappo and an amazing guy. And he said,
pitch Bitcoin to a group that I was with. And I was just like, okay, I get it. Because once I
explain it, like super well. And from there was like, okay, this is what I need to do. And it
reminded me a little bit of 2000 and the internet like super like early, even probably earlier to
be to be honest. But something where, you know, there was a lot of building to do and a lot of fun
to to have. And what really attracted me to to Bitcoin and crypto is I thought this is where I
would meet like the best people like the, you know, this is where the party would be. And actually,
it was true then. It's still true today. You know, if you go to a crypto conference, it's a real
party. You go to a normal internet conference. The party is not there anymore. So that's the
story and a challenge. Super happy to be here because, you know, the privilege to be here with you
today, come from that choice in 2014. And it was a good choice.
You know, it's funny. I went since I think he's obviously a rock star in Argentina. I think he's
often referred to as the Elon Musk of Argentina. I'm still quite amazed that I meet so many people
in the brother tech world that often have not heard of him. It's incredible. The outsized impact
he's had on crypto. I think many of the early founders of big public companies, we know now in
crypto, they got into the rabbit hole because of him, I mean, including you, right? So it's quite
an interesting impact he's had. But I think it's a super guy. I mean, I don't know him that well,
et cetera. But the super guy is super helpful, et cetera. So, you know, he does what he has to do.
He doesn't brag about it, et cetera. Like he's a model to follow.
This episode is brought to you by ACX compliance. Your one stop shop for all your crypto compliance
needs in the UAE and beyond. From Vara licensing support to crypto compliance training and
customized support, including crypto specialized transaction monitoring and SAR reporting filing
support. A six compliance has over 200 crypto compliance professionals that are 100% training
crypto and 100% focused on the crypto industry. If you're looking for a one stop shop to really
help you with all your crypto compliance needs, think ACX compliance. Find out more at www.accompliance.com.
So can we talk about ledger as well? To give us an update, I knew I think many of our users
will be familiar with it. I know they heard about ledger, but can you give me an update
up to our users as well? What is ledger and what are some of the latest developments going on with
ledger as a company and then we can talk about the product as well? Yeah, so ledger is a
security company at the heart. But for consumers and financial institution is the
most secure and best way, not only to keep your crypto assets safe, but to connect them to the
internet and to transact with them. That's the way you should think about it. So from a consumer
experience, what you end up with is a hardware wallet that connects to your phone or your computer.
And on your phone or your computer, you have a software, a ledger live, where are you going
to do your transaction? So it's very similar to the experience that you had with the iPod and iTunes,
for example. And interestingly enough, what people now need to have in mind is like ledger is always
referenced as the cold storage company, which is completely wrong. Because cold storage is
the idea that, oh, if I keep my private keys offline, then I'm really safe, which is a fallacy,
because then, okay, but what about doing a transaction now? If you bring them online, so then you're
not safe. So of course, you have to be safe all the time. And ledger is now a service. It's a
product and a service that allows you to keep your private keys safe when you don't use them,
but also safe when you use them and you want to transact with them. And so we've developed
through ledger live a whole bunch of all range of services at the service of the user to be able to
buy, sell, swap, stake, and sort of connect to any experience that you want to connect to,
any web three experience, blockchain experience, crypto experience, you could argue what that you
want to connect to in the safest possible way. So that's on the on the consumer side. And on the
enterprise side is exactly the same principle. And on the enterprise, maybe we'll talk about it later,
but we just launched, or we will soon announce that we launched ledger enterprise trade link,
which is an off exchange trading network, which is again, in this idea of you can use ledger,
not just to keep your crypto safe when it doesn't move, but also when you move and when you want to
trade on exchanges without the money being on an exchange, but the money is staying with your
favorite or you few favorites, regulated custodians. That's interesting. Actually,
maybe talk about this. I want to talk about stocks as well in a second. In this model,
basically, this is for your enterprise sales. So how would I work in practice? So I'm able to
keep my private keys and actually keep the assets safe while I'm interacting with various exchanges.
Yeah, 100%. So, you know, with FTX, the problem was the,
I say it was a very, very good exchange. You could, you know, a very good trading platform.
But the danger was coming from the counterparty risk of leaving your money on the exchange. And so,
a lot of financial institutions lost a lot of money because when the program happened,
the money was sort of stuck with the exchange. And actually, in crypto, you always have this where,
you know, the exchange also has the money, which is something that you don't find,
you know, in trade fight, in traditional finance, there is a segregation of duty where
the money is with the regulatory custodian, the exchange does the trade, etc. So what we're trying
to replicate here is really the segregation of duty that, you know, happen in traditional finance,
in a way that is 100% supported by pure technology where actually ledger doesn't interfere in the
trade. We're just providing the security platform that helps with the trade. And so basically,
you have three parties. I'll give you the simple version, but you have, you know,
people with the money, you have the regulatory custodian, and you got the exchange. And basically,
the money goes into the regulatory custodian. The regulatory custodian has a link to the exchange
through ledger enterprise. The link is super easy to install. It's an API call. And the money never
leaves the regulatory custodian. But on behalf of the customer, the regulatory custodian can place
trading orders on the exchange and clearing sets of them happen on the platform. So it's really
beautiful is something where we take zero. So we don't charge for the service. We take zero fees.
So actually, that's my main setting point, like we charge zero for this. And the business model is
the same as we had before, which is our customers are regulatory custodians, and they use ledger
technology in order to now also access this network. And regulatory custodians don't have to run
everything that they have on ledger enterprise. They can just use ledger enterprise to access
the trading network for the funds that need to access the trading network.
In this example, you know, Pascal, like who would sign the transaction, the person actually owns
actually the obviously the regulatory custodian will have the API call going on with the various
exchanges. But let's say to approve a transaction, do you need the end user to approve it? Or everything
will be done directly by the custodian, because it's an enterprise model. So the order will come from
the money manager to order will go to the regulatory custodian will execute the order
with the exchange. So and again, ledger has got nothing to do in that flow. We just providing the
tech that supports the flow. So at no time, we are here to approve a transaction, etc. We are
fully a technology platform. And the even the contracts, we have a contract with the regulatory
custodian. We have a technology contract with the exchange that does the API call, but we don't
have financial duties to this. And the financial contracts are between money, custodian and exchange.
And on this point, sorry, I want to talk about the retail offering in a second, but on this point,
because we want it, how do you believe the product will be different from some of the other offerings
in the market? For example, fire blocks and their own technology stack on this, or even Coinbase that
has their also their new Web3 wallet. I forgot the name now. How do you how do you think that how do
you position ledger compared to some of the offerings in the market on the enterprise side?
What's very difficult with crypto in general is that you have like many products and
they kind of look similar while being very different. And I think everything you just listed now are
products that kind of look the same, but actually in the end are very different. Like we do something
that is very new, but the market doesn't know how to do because we can help someone that has money
to use multiple custodians to actually bid on multiple exchanges. And actually, we are the only
one able to do this. And of course, to do the clearing and settlement of exchange and to charge
zero fees. So when you add all of these together, nobody else can can actually do this in the market.
Everyone is either stuck in their own custodian. So they will say, you know, off exchange may be
trading, but all the money goes into my custodian. So you don't have the choice of having multiple
custodian. They will also say, and by the way, we charge you whatever beeps per trade and we
charge zero, et cetera. So in the end, I think we are the most secure, most reliable, where we
interfere less with the business model of the trade, because we charge zero, and where in the end,
the customer has more options in terms of what custody partner they want to use and access to
the most liquidity. And this, I presume, you know, works with all the big tokens. And I presume from
a D5 perspective, obviously the centralized exchanges, but how do you guys approach in D5,
for example, on another perspective? Well, so this is obviously a product aimed at centralized
exchanges, right? Like, you know, because the counterparty risk for a decentralized exchange
doesn't exist in the same way. I mean, it doesn't exist because coins are, you know, on chain.
And so the trade link is for centralized exchanges to connect to defying a ledger enterprise as
another range of services. And so, you know, so you can connect all of your divide to your ledger
enterprise. Should you want to, but I would say that's a different product set or as these are
different features. Similarly, you can do your staking also sort of natively into ledger enterprise.
So ledger enterprise is a security platform, on top of which you can be all, you know, different
verticals of different, so with different features, different products, depending on what is your
strategy. Right now, trade link is really for those that train on centralized exchanges.
They still hold like 90 to 95 or 95 percent of the everyday trading volume. So, and, you know,
and Binance must be like 80 percent of this, you know. So, so we're really trying to address that
issue. And, you know, what happened in the past, we, you know, post FTX is like a lot of people are
not trading on some exchanges anymore, because they are afraid of that number one that comes
up at the risk, but they're also they're afraid of, you know, what would the regulator would say
if they knew that the coins were actually on the exchange. And, you know, sometimes our industry,
because it lacks regulation, sometimes you have an anticipation of regulation. And so, therefore,
you have a bunch of people not doing anything because they wait for regular regulation clarity.
And so, ledger trade link, ledger enterprise trade link is a bit, is an answer to this,
which is to say, hey, you don't even need to wait for regulation because when regulation hit,
this is exactly what they would want. And so, we unlock, we unlock a lot of potential and we,
we're talking with a lot of liquidity partners and they say, but, okay, what kind of volume are
you going to bring us? And the kind of volume that we bring to, you know, one specific partner,
we're talking between two and five billion dollars of assets to be traded on their platform.
So, we're talking big money because it's unlocking, you know, really big potential.
Absolutely. And can you hear me more? I've seen recently, there was an announcement where I think
many of us are being crypto for a long time. We know the ledger nano's, but obviously,
you guys have longed ledger stacks. Can you maybe share about what, what stacks is and how is it
different from the previous models of ledger nano's that many people may be familiar with?
Yeah, 100%. So, look, I bet that your fund today looks very different from your fund in the year
2000. And the reason why is because, you know, software evolves very quickly. What you can do
is blockchain today, it's very different from what you could do with blockchain in 2014 or 2008.
And so, therefore, you know, it is not, it is very a normal that the hardware part has to evolve
also with the software and with the way that people use their crypto. And so, the last product
that we released I think was sort of, you know, 18, 19, like, you know, nano X, nano S plus,
and that was an evolution of the, of the nano S. So, everybody, I think on your podcast knows
this product, but for the people who don't know, you know, this is, this is quite a revolutionary
product. It looks like a USB stick. It is not a USB stick. It is something with, you know, real
security inside that helps you, again, protect your keys when they're not moving and protect
your keys when you want to do a transaction. And these products are great today, still,
and, you know, we highly recommend them. But some of our customers were asking for more and also
usage are a bit different now. Most of what it is is really people were asking for bigger screen,
you know, because on the nano X is true that the screen is rather small. And so, you know,
if you don't see well, for example, you know, this is, this is a difficulty. But also, as you know,
we went into the smart contract era, we went into, you know, transactions that are more complex
every day, etc. So you actually need more space just to display the one transaction. So you know
what you say. What is very important to understand in crypto is if you don't know what you say and
you're at risk, blind signing is a problem. Nobody, nobody should do blind signing. People do blind
signing because they sacrifice security for convenience. We support blind signing in the sense that
our customers are asking for us to enable blind signing. We think it's wrong from a security
standpoint, but we also want to indulge our customers. However, we are pushing clear signing
and typically we stacks. This is one push towards clear signing. So our users, the people that we
try to protect, we protect them every time. And so you should be able at some point to clear sign
every transaction, but transaction getting more complex. You need a bigger screen. And what we
really did with stacks, we really worked on UX and UI and really worked on the product. You know,
one of the, you know, problem of a young industry is, it's usually very ticking and it's very normal.
Again, when industries are born, they're born because thanks to engineers. And so, you know, the
first, the first draft of the industry is highly technical. And so just like the internet in '95
or '92, like only highly technical people or, you know, geeky people could really understand,
connect, et cetera, et cetera. But mass adoption comes when all of this is productized in a way
that general population can actually understand what the product is for and understand how to
use it in a very simple manner. So stacks is really a step at this. We try to do a product that is
more for the mass. Still, I mean, the best products, period in the market right now,
for everyone, even the tech, even the geeky, et cetera, et cetera, no problem. But also,
appealing for the mass, where certainly, you know, the onboarding, which is a big program for crypto,
how do you deal with your 24 words? You know, all of this has been super streamlined into,
you know, onboarding people into self-guestity. I'm keen to use it. I would say, like, one of the
problems I would say even as a user previously is always, like the transaction, even the address
would never fit on one screen in the old ledger. You have to see it. It's complicated. I mean,
I always give the analogy that my mom, who's by the way, my biggest fan of all my podcasts,
watches all my episodes, I don't think she understands anything we talk about. But I should never be
able to use a ledger, you know, but she's keen to learn more about crypto. You know, so it's very
interesting on SACS and I look forward to experimenting with it. Let's go.
I think I give you a stack, no? Not yet, not yet. So I'd love to try one.
Okay. I need to fix that. I need to fix that. I was 100% sure. I was 100% sure I gave you.
I'll try one. I'll give you the feedback as well. I'm sorry. Yeah, absolutely. Why do you brought
something that is very important, which, you know, I think about a lot is you mentioned,
obviously, the debate between security and convenience and user experience.
When you look at the future of crypto, let's say five years from now, where do you think that
midpoint would be the right perfect mix or do you believe for they will be different
composition of security and convenience, depending on the audience you're targeting?
Well, I mean, I would say right now the market is asking consumers, users to compromise.
Hey, you know, if you want real convenience, you have to compromise in security. If you want
full security, you have to compromise in convenience, et cetera. You know, I think where the market is
going is to a point where we will be, ledger will be able to build a product where you won't
have to compromise either on security nor on convenience. You will be a product that is both
secure and convenient. I think ledger stacks is almost there. And I think that the next versions
of stacks will be even better. And at some points, you're going to have a device that works extremely
conveniently while being more secure than your phone. Actually, because people sometimes say to me,
oh, you know, ledger is very hard to use. I say, well, you know, I'm not sure, actually.
When I use ledger, I think it's even the nano X today, I think it's actually quite easy to use,
but it depends what you compare it to. If you compare using a clash of clan on your phone,
yeah, okay, maybe, you know, stacks in nano X are a little harder to use.
Now think about using something that has to be secure on your phone. You need two FAs. You need
like a bunch of stuff. It's not super easy to connect. If you want to set up an account on an
exchange, you need to do a KYC. I mean, you need to do a lot of things that are slow you down,
that are actually quite cumbersome, et cetera. And so it's sometimes not very easy. I was actually
having discussion with someone from the industry who went from Coinbase custody or Coinbase Prime
to ledger. They had 100% of the coins of Coinbase Prime, and then they do 50/50 using ledger.
And it was actually quite shocked to figure to find out that ledger was easier to use.
To use Coinbase Prime, it's not that easy to use and not to, you know, probably Coinbase can do
better on these or that. But the thing is, if you want to bring security in your Coinbase Prime,
you need to do several checks. You need to have two FAs. You need to ask for people IDs,
et cetera. You need to do all these things to bring security. And security has an, in fact,
on convenience. So I think what we're really trying to do for a consumer is a self custody
model that brings you absolute security, even with the 24 words and, you know, with ledger
recovery and those kind of things where we protect you against yourself, because we do get those
messages of, "I lost my ledger and my 24 words. Why do I do now?" So if you have a backup ledger
recovery, we're trying to solve that program for these people. And so if we have to protect
you against yourself, we have to make it super convenient. You know, again, you use the stacks
and for people, you know, you get one as soon as we're ready to ship after pre-orders, we should
be anytime soon now. And you really have to receive for yourself. Like, it's super easy to use now.
And, you know, when you talk about the future of custody, right? Obviously, you mentioned the
having a hardware wallet and, you know, the importance of it from a security perspective. And I get that.
But when you think about, again, the future of custody, do you believe that really
we will be using a physical wallet, whether it's our phone or ledger stocks or whatever it is,
to basically hold our digital assets? Or there'll be the compromise where people will do using some
of these software custody models are out there. Yes, you may need to do the 2FA. Yes, maybe there's
Google Authenticator and there's different security mechanisms. But at least for a lot of people,
the risk of losing the private keys is something that they're more afraid of than, actually,
the having, holding your private keys. Yeah, so look, there are two models that always,
there is custody and self custody. So either you trust someone with your private keys or you
keep your private keys. And there are many shades of gray in the middle. It's like, you know, I can
share some of my key with you, et cetera, et cetera. And then it's all about, you know, compromise and
what you want to do. I think that cryptocurrency exists, Bitcoin exists only because if it's in
if it's in self custody, if it's to be in custody, there is no point to the model. You know, it's a
peer-to-peer payment network. And so if you cannot be peer-to-peer, if you don't own your private keys,
what's the point of Bitcoin? I mean, and it's not even like a philosophical reasoning that I'm doing
now. It's a pure, you know, practical, technical, like, you know, this is how it works. Now, you know,
in the future, I think people will hold a bunch of crypto, a bunch of crypto assets, a bunch of
digital assets. And then the question is, will everything be in self custody, or will you have
some in custody, others in self custody, et cetera? Okay, so probably be, you know, both, like, you
need services for some things. You know, if you have a lot of wealth in Bitcoin, maybe you put some
at the bank, maybe you keep some yourself, like, you know, there are many ways of doing this.
But the important thing to know is in the future, people have now the choice, you know, before
digital assets were necessarily in custody of someone, either it's a bank, either it's Google,
Apple, et cetera. Now you have an option to keep them in self custody. Now, when you think about
keeping them in self custody, the question becomes, okay, boy, do I need like a hardware? So I give
you the short answer, it's yes, like, there's no other way than having secure hardware to secure.
Your digital assets, your coins, and everything that is in your digital life, and that you want
to secure your phone today, your phone and computer are not good hardware, good, not good security
hardware to secure this. Why? Because you can attack them from the operating system, and as soon
as you're in the operating system, everything that runs on top of the operating system,
which is everything is by definition, unsecure. And so therefore, you cannot leave everything
on your phone or your computer. So now, if it's real self custody, it means, you know, where are
the private keys, et cetera? You need to have a hardware with it. Now there is something coming
our way, which is account abstraction. And so in your question, maybe you also refer to this to
say, hey, but there is this account abstraction thing that might indicate that actually you don't
need hardware anymore, because now everything is software. So again, it's a question of compromise.
So first of all, you cannot run every coin, you cannot run really Bitcoin today in account
abstraction, account abstraction is mainly for Ethereum. There are other technologies that are
similar to account abstraction that can do a little bit more, a little bit less, et cetera. But you
always have a compromise on usability. Now, if you want the world of what you can do with ledger
today is like, I want all my coins, I want to be able to do everything, I want to be able to connect
with everything, et cetera, there is no other way than ledger and secure hardware. Everything else
is a compromise on what you can do. The coinbase wallet that you're referring to, that has done
some account extraction on base, you know, their account base layer two, you know, that's all good
and well, but it's a subset of what you can do with crypto is very limited in terms of the
application that you can run on top of that. It's good, et cetera. And also when it comes to
account abstraction and final point, you sort of need like a source of trust, because an account
abstraction is basically a contract that says that you can only do certain things with your coins,
and so therefore it's hard to act. But how do you define the contract? And how do you sign the
definition of that contract? So with that, you still need secure hardware at the beginning to
define the contract. And finally, even if you run an account abstraction, well-defined with the
hardware at the beginning, with set of rules, et cetera, and you still run this on your phone
or your computer, you in the end have something that's called man in the middle attack, which
means that you cannot trust whether it's on the screen of your phone. You cannot trust what is
on the screen of your computer. Therefore, you don't really know where you're sending the coins.
And even with an account abstraction, you will be blind signing the shit up everything. And so
blind signing is something really crazy. It's like every time you blind sign something, you're like,
you press the button and you hope that your coins arrive, you know, at the right for all destination.
Can you imagine for a benefit of our audience, maybe just giving a quick summary of what is
account abstraction and the role that smart contracts play instead of maybe private keys,
just maybe the one minute summary. So I want to make sure everybody's on top of it on that
perspective. Yeah, sorry. So if you see this as a problem with security, like every time you
want to have a discussion, you need to, you know, go down the rabbit hole and it gets very complex,
et cetera. Netnet, the best solution that is the most secure, that gives you real self custody on
every coin, et cetera, is hardware wallets today and it's ledger and ledger stack number one. So
that's that's my answer. And now when it comes to account abstraction, account abstraction is this
idea of having a wallet where rules are preset. And so the wallets cannot do anything else. But
the rules that have been defined for the wallet, which limit the possibility of, you know, hiking
the wallet on the phone to have the wallet do something else because then it becomes impossible
because the wallet is a structure to do like a certain kind of functions. But again, the one
thing that the wallet still cannot do is fight the man in the middle attack, meaning that even if
the rules are structured as soon as you type an address or whatever you see on your phone,
you're not really sure that it's true. So you don't really know where the coins will end. And that's
the big problem. Yeah. Yeah, a lot of interest, I think for interest readers, there's a lot of
information on this online that can find about account abstraction in the world, smart contracts.
But let's go to one last question before we want to find one question. It's something I've been
wondering for a long time. How come today, when I look at my iPhone, for example, how come companies
like Apple haven't come up with their own, you know, hardware custody? I mean, when you think
about your biggest competitor, don't you think that like these phone companies could be the ones
offering hardware wallets at scale? And this could be big adoption and potentially a big competitor
for two ledger as well? Well, I got two letters to answer that question. AI, I think Apple is
busier trying to figure out like, you know, what to do with AI on their phones than building a
hardware wallet, which seems to be like a niche category for them compared to having all their
phones AI enabled. And, you know, Apple is trying to solve very big problems already, not to say
that what we're solving is not a big problem. It is a big problem, but it's still a very niche
activity in a sense that, you know, when you think about the people that are crypto holders,
we say that there are 500, 600 billion in the panic. Most of these people have their
wealth on an exchange, which is something that you shouldn't do. You shouldn't take that risk.
If you trade, sure, put your money on the exchange, except if you're a financial institution,
now use trade link. But if you're an individual, put your money on the exchange trade, and as soon
as the trade is over, move your money back to the security of your ledger. But right now,
most people actually leave their money on an exchange. You know, that's number one. There is a
subset of people that actually hold their private keys. But when you start to looking at buy addresses
and see the wealth that they have for addresses, you will find that they're 20 million. If I'm
very generous, like 25 million people that have like real wealth on an address, which means like
more than a thousand dollars, it's not a lot of people. So right now, actually, the market is
still very niche. We sold seven million devices now. So it's a lot of devices for us.
It's very nothing for Apple. Apple sells 250 million iPhones a year, 160 million
airports a year, 45 million Apple watches a year. So look, and so that's that. And also,
technologically speaking, what we do is fairly complex because what you have in terms of
security is not just a secure element. It's the operating system that you run into it.
And that is proprietary to ledger. And the operating system start to be very complex because
when you want to support just Bitcoin, that's easy enough. If you support Bitcoin and everything else
start to become very complex. And the operations that we have just to make the operating system
is really becoming a product at ledger right now. And it's just saying, you know, you talk about
iOS, you talk about Android, soon we will rebrand our operating system with a good name. But this
is one of the main products at ledger, which is the operating system. So that's even for Apple.
That's not easy to do. Apple can do anything they want. Okay, that they have the money. If they want
to do this, they'll do it still. It's not an easy problem to solve. And then there is a problem,
like, you know, if you say you lose your crypto, and you have your Apple hardware in your Apple,
and something happens to your crypto, then you turn to Apple. Do you think Apple won that kind
of fire? I don't think so. Yeah, exactly. It's very interesting what you mentioned. What we
often think crypto, you know, the world, the world turns around the crypto ecosystem. But actually,
there's so many other things going on. AI is one of them you mentioned, which we look, I think
sometimes even myself, I have to bring myself back to reality saying actually nobody cares about
crypto except losers like us or in it, you know, so it's a very interesting on that perspective.
One last question pass out does not do with crypto, but it's about France. I know when people
think about let's say big web tree companies in France, they often ledger would be one of them
that will pop up. We've been recently seeing a revival of the French ecosystem in the sense
of these companies like yours, I've been growing. So I was reading about Mistral and AI field and
others are going to be going with the Olympics now in Paris. What's your view in Paris, let's say
France as a tech and not only crypto, but tech ecosystem of the future. And let's be honest.
Well, I mean, TVD because, you know, in the past 20 years, like I said, only crypto went public
at the nest act. So, and if you look at the French ecosystem in terms of exits, you know,
who had like a full exit for billions of dollars, et cetera, like not many companies.
So if you, you know, raising money, running a good business, et cetera, a bunch of companies
have done, you know, but, but full exits, a successful exit or even, you know, become even
better, like becoming the 100 pound gorilla and starting to acquire other companies.
Nobody has managed to actually do this. So I would say, you know, the ecosystem is here.
It's better than what he has been, but he still has a lot to achieve.
I was actually checking the market cap of SAP the other day. Do you know the market cap of SAP?
So I think, and you will correct me if I'm wrong, but I think it's 250 billion dollars. So actually,
it's pretty good. And when I checked, I remember checking this in 2008 or 2010 or something like
that, when I was still like, pretty, it was 50 billion. So actually the SAP market cap like grew
a lot between in the past, you know, 10, 12 years. But SAP is the only like, I would say what,
web one company that, that sort of still exists in Europe and that is one of the,
one of the juggernodes and that has like MNF arms and that acquires companies, et cetera,
et cetera. You know, you Europe in general and France. We've not been very good at building
the big companies, you know, the Google of the world. So, you know, is France going to build one
in the next 20 years? I surely hope so. I surely hope Ledger is going to be that one or at least,
you know, sort of one of them. We have amazing engineers in France. I think this is what you see
with Pascual, which is the quantum company. I think this is what you see with mistyle and AI
because, you know, French engineers have always been, you know, the top of the sword. But the problem
with French engineering is sometimes it builds amazing technology, amazing products, but we don't
know how to market and sell them. And sometimes you lose to inter-technology products that have better
marketing and salesmanship. What I'm trying to fix with Ledger is to bring the best of the French
engineers. And typically, when it comes to secure hardware, that whole security industry is really
a French excellence in terms of engineering and, you know, it's been proven in the past by other
companies like Dallas, Gémerto, Idenia, Exotax et al. So, we're taking from that excellence,
taking from this technology and bringing them to these new worlds of, you know, sort of blockchain
technology, but also trying to bring what is best in terms of marketing and sales and, you know,
with people like Ian Rogers, et cetera, you know, coming from, like, real storytellers,
like people that know how to build a brand, tell a story, et cetera, and make Ledger like a global
brand and a global category leader. That's what we're trying to do. So, if you take the best
everywhere, you can find them and you bring them together to build a global company. I think this
is how it works. And I think this is typically the past that Ledger is on. Execution is extremely
difficult. Whether we succeed or not in the future is TBD. We'll see. We're going to do our best.
We think this is the right strategy, but, you know, future will fail and customers will decide.
And for other companies, you know, I think they start with the best engineers. Now, Pascal is very
fresh. Pascal is very fresh. Mistral is very fresh. And, honestly, Mistral, you know, is the name
of a wind in France. So, I wish them luck. I wish them luck to all of them. And I hope that they
transform what is technology into product and product into sales, you know. Yeah, absolutely.
I think you're so right. You know, I've met so many amazing French engineers over the years.
In fact, also, a lot of them going to finance, right, from derivatives and others. And I think
it's what you mentioned is that sales element often is missing. But time will tell. Pascal,
time to go with my regular fire round, round of questions. So, I'm going to ask you what
quick questions I need to one or two word answers. And we're going to go through them pretty quickly.
Hope you're ready. Ready. Let's do it. Pascal, what amazes you the most about the crypto industry?
Well, like I said before, I think the people. I think the people are amazing. You know,
and sometimes too toxic. But even the toxicity, you know, I find it, you know, the parochism of
humanity is like, you know, it's so much emotion that is going into crypto that you have the best
and the worst. And, honestly, I take it all. Sometimes, you know, people are unkind to me
on the X. But I think it's part of the game. And also, I understand the emotion behind it. I understand
the rage and the frustration because when people are in crypto, it's they come with passion. And so,
I think to me, that's why I like the most. Let's continue. What is the one thing that keeps you
up at night? Nothing. I sleep super well. You know, the only thing that keeps me up at night is,
you know, my family want to make sure that they're right, you know, if I for them, the rest, I don't
care. What's your favorite thing to do on a weekend when you're not busy working on crypto?
Well, it depends. If I'm super tired, I really like to do nothing. And I, you know, I love doing
nothing. And, but if I'm up for it, you know, you know, a weekend in the business, great.
Here we go. Favorite, favorite restaurant. I know you're a restaurant owner, as you mentioned
before in the Marianne Paris. If there's one restaurant you think is outside of yours,
that really is your favorite globally. Which one is it? Well, really, right now, we've got a
cool look here for longosteria in Paris. It's in the neo-tertia, not long. LVM at your tail,
longosteria is an institution coming from Milan. It's an Italian restaurant. And the one that I
have in Paris, I've never been to the one in Milan, but apparently I've been told that the
one in Paris is even better. And to tell you the truth, it's really my favorite restaurant right now.
And Pascal, are you good cook? And if, if yes, what's your, what's your favorite dish to cook?
Well, I'm not sure I'm a good cook. I'm an okay cook. And I do eggs really well.
Eggs, really. Here we go. The simplicity of it. What is the one crypto CEO that impresses you the most?
That's a great question. You know, there've been a few
arter aids of, as always, been one of the smartest, I think, you know, very, very sharp.
And also, you know, when you see arter, he's joking, like, you know, but he's very smart,
very, very deep. I understand crypto better than most. Arthur was always very impressive.
We started with Win Says, of course. Like I said, you know, I came to crypto because of the people.
So you meet some of the, you know, brightest minds in crypto. And there are not, I could go on and
on because there are a lot of people that I've found in the years, very impressive, including you,
and I'm not just, you know, saying this, I mean it. So again, that's why I came to be with great
people, impressive people, fun people. I appreciate it. I appreciate it. Let's continue that the
I have to say, but on Arthur Hayes, totally agree. I think people see him as a party guy,
but actually he's one of the smartest guys in the industry by a mile as well.
Pascal, if there's one asset, one digital asset, you can hold for the next 10 years
and not be able to sell what crypto asset would that be? Bitcoin.
I could have better that would be your answer. You're an avid skier. What's your favorite place to
ski? Tin, so it's near Valizair. It's the same value. Tin, T, I, J, N, E, S, Tin. It's a fantastic
resort. It's my blessing and my doom. It's so amazing to ski there and it's my doom because
then I don't want to ski anywhere else anymore. You just mentioned before, best one of the
favorite things to do is spending a weekend in Ibiza. What's the one thing about Ibiza people get
wrong? Ibiza, people get wrong? Yeah. Too much healing, my friend. At some point, you get to
stop eating. Eating, you go. Eating is a nasty part of Ibiza. Everybody's eating all the time,
so it's good, but you know. Exactly. You mentioned before storytelling. What is the one company you
think outside of Ledger that gets storytelling and crypto marketing right?
Look, I think Binance to be honest. Really? Yeah. My father always said to me, still today says to
me, only the results matter. If you look at Binance results, they're doing something right. It doesn't
seem like that. You would look at Coinbase and be like, "Well, better marketing, et cetera. Great
advertising, et cetera." Binance doesn't do much, but they got such a market share. So there is
something that they do that is touching the communities, that is touching the people, people
trust Binance, go on Binance, et cetera. There is something that they obviously do that makes them
the best, and they're not like a little the best. They're the best best. They're 10x the next guy.
So what they're doing is very, very impressive, and sometimes you just need to look at the results
and the results tell you like, "Who is the best?" And also, everybody thought that they would go down
after what happened with CZ, et cetera, et cetera. They didn't. They maintain market share,
they lost a little bit, and then they grew their market share back, et cetera. It is quite crazy,
the velocity that this company has. It is insane, the kind of money that they're making. They don't
disclose the numbers, but I think I know, and it's insane. And really, other companies are doing
great, and Coinbase is great. It's amazing. They have insane numbers. Binance is more insane by a lot.
I agree. It's incredible. I mean, depending on the week, anywhere from 70, 75% of global volume,
it's absolutely incredible on my perspective. You mentioned X before Twitter. If you had one
piece of advice to Elon Musk regarding how to improve X, what would that be? First of all,
I wouldn't dare, because, you know, he is the god of business, and so I would not dare giving him
any advice. And also, I think what he's doing with X is really fantastic. So, you know, no advice to,
I would ask him for a piece of advice, I would say. I cannot say to say it, please, please,
please tell me what I should do. I love it. And finally, Pascal, the CEO of Ledger.
Pascal, a typical question anybody comes on my show. If you could have lunch or dinner with
one person that are alive, lunch or dinner with one person that are alive, who would it be?
Oh, yeah, yeah, it's a very tough question. Dead or alive, lunch? I don't know. If I want to be a
little pedantic, I would say, I don't know, I like to have dinner with Verder. You know,
it's a field of the four of the 18th century. You know, I think in the world that we live in where
everybody is going behind Rousseau and Mattus, I mean, you know, this is really the field of the
first that are influencing the world economic forum. I'm much more of a Verder type of guy.
And, you know, Verter used to say, I like my iron centering, GEM, Moséco de Feer. You know,
I really like the time that we live in. You know, I think people should read Verder, GEM,
Moséco de Feer. (speaks French)
The only important thing is to take care of your garden, you know, and to basically to work.
So, yeah, okay, if I dinner, I would have dinner with Verter. It would be fascinating, I think.
If we log dinner with a lot of bottles of wine, I'm sure, from that perspective,
Pascal, it's great to have you on the show. I think it was over now a year,
you haven't been on the show, so great to have you on. Where can people find out more about you,
about ledger and stocks and some of the offerings you guys have?
Well, people can find me on X, beware of people that impersonate me, but I've got like several
checkmarks that make sure that it's my account, etc. So follow that one, not the others.
Ledger.com, Ledger Academy, everything that we talked about in terms of the difference between
hardware wallet, software wallet, account abstraction, etc. All of this is documented on Ledger Academy.
Our CTO, Charles Gimme has wrote like a lot of papers about this. If you want to know about
quantum computing, attacking your ledger, again, we have a blog post about this. We have so much
content on Ledger, really, anything you want to know, just check us out. That's my recommendation.
Amazing. Thank you, Pascal. Great. Thank you. Hopefully, this was as you guys enjoyed,
listening to this as much as I had. Very exciting developments. Make sure to also check out,
guys, my YouTube page, a lot of interesting content there. Thank you very much, once again,
for all your support of making this one of the best podcasts, not only on crypto, but really now
that we're in the top 5% globally of all podcasts and Spotify. Thank you very much, everybody.
And see you guys soon for another episode of the future of Money Podcasts. See you guys soon.